Guide to the C. Vann Woodward Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Writings, 1935-1998; Series II
  - Unpublished Writings
    - 1950s
      - American Historiography, 1929-1954 (Box 73, Folder 126)
      - American History in Europe (Box 73, Folder 126)
      - Civil Rights and the Ghost of Thaddeus Stevens (Box 73, Folder 126)
      - Commonwealth Lectures, University of London [Lecture I: The South as an Approach to the American Legend] (Box 73, Folder 126)
      - Critics and Criticism (Box 73, Folder 126)
      - Critics of Foreign Policy (Box 73, Folder 126)
      - "Deliberate Speed" vs. "Majestic Instancy" (Box 73, Folder 126)
      - The Disturbed Southerners (Box 73, Folder 127)
      - The Eccentricity of American History (Box 73, Folder 127)
      - Hidden Issues of Reconstruction (Box 73, Folder 127)
      - Historians Since the War (Box 73, Folder 127)
      - The Impending Crisis in Higher Education (Box 73, Folder 127)
      - Morality and Self Interest in Foreign Policy (Box 73, Folder 127)
      - The Myth of the Garden (Box 73, Folder 127)
      - New Perspectives on Southern History (Box 73, Folder 127)
      - The New Reconstruction (Box 73, Folder 127)
      - North Going South (Box 73, Folder 127)
      - Oxford (Box 73, Folder 127)
      - The South and the Law of the Land (Box 73, Folder 127)
      - Anti-Americanism in Japan and England (Box 73, Folder 127)
      - Untitled (forward, and introduction) (Box 73, Folder 127)
    - 1960-1975
      - The African Diaspora in America (Box 73, Folder 128)
      - Alexander M. Bickel, 1924-1974 (Box 73, Folder 128)
      - American Attitude Toward History (Box 73, Folder 128)
      - American History and the Social Sciences (Box 73, Folder 128)
      - The Antislavery Myth (Box 73, Folder 128)
      - Change Over Time (Box 73, Folder 128)
      - Comment on Meier's Paper (Box 73, Folder 128)
      - The Eccentricity of American History (Box 73, Folder 128)
      - The Erosion of Academic Privileges and Immunities (Box 73, Folder 128)
      - A Farewell to the Class of the Confrontation (Box 73, Folder 128)
      - From the First Reconstruction to the Second (Box 73, Folder 128)
      - Is America by Nature a Violent Society? (Box 73, Folder 129)
      - Is History Obsolete? (Box 73, Folder 129)
      - The Misbehavioral Muse (Box 73, Folder 129)
      - Noble Dreams and Great Expectations (Box 73, Folder 129)
      - The Other South: Southern Dissenters in the Nineteenth Century (Box 73, Folder 129)
      - Populists-Then and Now (Box 73, Folder 129)
      - Psychohistory and Quantohistory: Noble Dreams and Great Expectations (Box 73, Folder 129)
      - The Reinterpretation of American History (Box 73, Folder 129)
      - Salute to the Amistad Research Center (Box 73, Folder 129)
      - The Second Reconstruction In Retrospect (Box 73, Folder 130)
      - Segregation in Historical Perspective (Box 73, Folder 130)
      - Southern Styles: A Typology (Box 73, Folder 130)
      - That Other Impeachment and its "Lessons" (Box 73, Folder 130)
      - Turning Point in the Negro Revolution (Box 73, Folder 130)
      - What Became of the Nineteen Sixties? (Box 73, Folder 130)
      - Why the Southern Renaissance? (Box 73, Folder 130)
      - Yale Law School Lecture (Box 73, Folder 130)
      - Untitled [four writings] (Box 73, Folder 130)
    - 1980s
      - Golden Anniversaries: CVW + SHA Convention, November 1984 (Box 74, Folder 131)
      - History and the Falsified Past (Box 74, Folder 131)
      - Images for Arkansas (Box 74, Folder 131)
      - Prejudices of a Historian (Box 74, Folder 131)
      - Tribute and Jeremiad (Box 74, Folder 131)
    - 1990s
      - America as Metaphor (Box 74, Folder 132)
      - American Historians at Odds with Each Other (Box 74, Folder 132)
      - Baltimore's HLM (Box 74, Folder 132)
      - Comment on Robert Wiebe, "Nationalism in America" (Box 74, Folder 132)
      - Doctorate in 7 or 8 Years! (Box 74, Folder 132)
      - Edmund Wilson's Patriotic Gore (Box 74, Folder 132)
      - Exile at Yale [regarding Robert Penn Warren] (Box 74, Folder 132)
      - A Few Words about Jefferson and Madison on Slavery (Box 74, Folder 132)
      - Freedom Versus Responsibility At Yale (Box 74, Folder 132)
      - Help from Historians (Box 74, Folder 132)
      - The South, Then and Now (Box 74, Folder 132)
      - Universities and Democracies (Box 74, Folder 132)
      - Lectures [promotional materials], 1954-1995, undated (Box 74, Folder 133)
- Subjects, 1947-1997; Series III
  The series is arranged alphabetically by topic. There is particularly substantive correspondence from historians commenting on a draft of Woodward's presidential address to the American Historical Association in 1969. The commentors include Charles Barker, Peter Gay, John Higham, Richard Hofstadter, George Pierson, David Potter, and Boyd Shafer. There is also substantive correspondence between Woodward and Stanley Elkins and Eric McKitrick, regarding their dissertations, and monographs each worked on individually. Woodward recorded notes of a meeting and conversation he and several others had with Alger Hiss in 1959. Documentation of Woodward's involvement with the NAACP in school desegregation cases includes correspondence, mostly incoming, and "The Background of the Abandonment of Reconstruction," an essay written by Woodward for the NAACP. The International Council on the Future of the University, with which Woodward was affiliated from its inception, contains mostly incoming correspondence and collected materials, but there are scattered writings and correspondence by him.
  - American Historical Association
    - Presidential address [correspondence from historians from whom Woodward asked for review and criticisms], 1969 (Box 75, Folder 1)
    - Radical caucus, 1969, undated (Box 75, Folder 2)
  - Analogues and southern identity ["to be delivered"; mostly handwritten notes], undated (Box 75, Folder 3)
  - Beard, Charles [correspondence re: volume on Beard], 1947-1948, undated (Box 75, Folder 4)
  - Brandeis University Summer School Insititute on the American South, 1957 (Box 75, Folder 5)
  - Burns, Ken [mostly re: the Civil War PBS series], 1986-1994 (Box 75, Folder 6)
  - Civil rights movement [mostly clippings], 1965 (Box 75, Folder 7)
  - Disney [Manassas battlefield], 1994, undated (Box 75, Folder 8)
  - Edelstein, Tilden, 1974 (Box 75, Folder 9)
  - Elkins, Stanley and Eric McKitrick, 1955-1960, undated (Box 75, Folder 10)
  - Europeans in America [handwritten bibliography], undated (Box 75, Folder 11)
  - Examination questions, 1947-1954, undated (Box 75, Folder 12)
  - Festschrift, 1982 (Box 75, Folder 13)
  - Free travel of scientists, 1969 (Box 75, Folder 14)
  - Glenn, W. W. [re: publication of the diary], 1957 (Box 75, Folder 15)
  - Harcourt, Brace and Company [re: A History of the United States], 1957-1959, undated (Box 75, Folder 16)
  - Hiss, Alger [Woodward's notes of conversation with Hiss], 1959 (Box 75, Folder 17)
  - History enrollment surveys, 1969, undated (Box 76, Folder 18)
  - History 164 [History of the South Since 1877; reading list], undated (Box 76, Folder 19)
  - History project for House Judiciary Committee, 1974, undated (Box 76, Folder 20)
  - Hofstader, Richard [re: death, includes Woodward eulogy], 1970 (Box 76, Folder 21)
  - India trip [in February 1988], 1986-1989, undated (Box 76, Folder 22)
  - International Conference on Comparative Slavery [correspondence, materials about; conference was not held], 1967, undated (Box 76, Folder 23)
  - International Council on the Future of the University, 1974-1982, undated (Box 76, Folder 24 - 26)
  - International Council on the Future of the University, 1974-1982, undated (Box 77, Folder 27)
  - Jim Crow laws, 1969, undated (Box 77, Folder 28)
  - John Harvard Library, 1958-1961 (Box 77, Folder 29 - 30)
  - Joint review of American history text, undated (Box 77, Folder 31)
  - Kellogg, Charles Flint [writing on the Blair Bill], undated (Box 77, Folder 32)
  - Lesher, Stephen, George Wallace American Populist [re: by Lesher his use of Dan Carter's book proposal, and Woodward's review of the book], 1994, undated (Box 77, Folder 33 - 34)
  - Lowenheim, Francis [re: charges against Franklin Delano Roosevelt Library], 1969, undated (Box 77, Folder 35)
  - Macune, C.W. [The Farmer's Alliance], undated (Box 77, Folder 36)
  - Multiculturalism in universities [correspondence re: lecture], 1992-1997, undated (Box 77, Folder 37)
  - Narrative history, 1980, 1983, undated (Box 78, Folder 38)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People [re: school desegregation cases, includes Woodward writing, "The Background of the Abandonment of Reconstruction"], 1953 (Box 78, Folder 39)
  - New York Times [advertisement on liberalism], 1988, undated (Box 78, Folder 40)
  - New Zealand trip, 1995 (Box 78, Folder 41)
  - Notable historians of North America [Woodward selections], 1953 (Box 78, Folder 42)
  - Ogden, C. K. [reminiscences about], 1958 (Box 78, Folder 43)
  - Oxford American lectures [correspondence], 1988-1989 (Box 78, Folder 44)
  - Oxford University visiting professorship [correspondence on a variety of topics], 1954-1955, undated (Box 78, Folder 45)
  - Ph.D. reading lists, 1952-1957, undated (Box 78, Folder 46)
  - Phi Beta Kappa [book committee], 1957-1959 (Box 78, Folder 47)
  - Prague, Leningrad, Moscow trip, 1988-1991, undated (Box 79, Folder 48 - 49)
  - Second Dartmouth Conference Japanese American Round Table, 1964, undated (Box 79, Folder 50)
  - Second term, Beginnings of Modern America [lecures and lecture notes?], undated (Box 79, Folder 51)
  - Slavery symposium [Princeton University Press], undated (Box 79, Folder 52)
  - South and myth [includes correspondence, writings, and collected materials], 1961-1965, undated (Box 79, Folder 53)
  - Tokyo seminar, 1953, undated (Box 79, Folder 54)
  - Transitional Year Program, Inc., 1966-1967, undated (Box 79, Folder 55)
  - United States Bicentennial [includes Woodward essay, The Time Has Come, the Walrus Said...; mostly essays by other historians], 1974-1976, undated (Box 79, Folder 56)
  - Voting rights act [Woodward's House subcommittee testimony], 1981 (Box 79, Folder 57)
  - Warren, Robert Penn [includes Woodward's introduction to John Brown ], 1987-1992, undated (Box 79, Folder 58)
- Research, 1873-1960; Series IV
  The series is arranged alphabetically by topic. The several folders containing applications Woodward made to foundations for research funding include statements by him, early in his career, of proposed research plans. The Research notes on personal papers collections are typed transcriptions of all, or portions, of letters found in various collections of which he made use in his research.
  - Debs, Eugene [correspondence about and notes], 1938-1939, undated (Box 80, Folder 1)
  - Funding [applications to agencies for research grants for work on a Eugene Debs biography, and The Origins of the New South ], 1938-1939, undated (Box 80, Folder 2)
  - Lilly Foundation [grant application to do a reappraisal of Reconstruction history], 1960 (Box 80, Folder 3)
  - Oberlin College library, 1952 (Box 80, Folder 4)
  - Research notes on personal paper collections, undated (Box 80, Folder 5 - 8)
  - Scharff, J. Thomas [typed copy of Montgomery Blair letter to Scharff], 1878 (Box 80, Folder 9)
  - Sumner, Charles papers [notes on, excerpts from], undated (Box 80, Folder 10)
  - Watson, Thomas [copy of Watson letter to J. R. Smith], 1908 (Box 80, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1873, 1949-1950, undated (Box 80, Folder 12)
  - Subject note card file, undated (Box 81–84)
- Yale University, 1944-1994; Series V
  The series is arranged alphabetically by topic. The folders of material on Herbert Aptheker contain clippings and correspondence related to the decision rendered against his application for a teaching appointment at Yale. Woodward chaired the committee that reached the decision. Materials related to Woodward's work in preparing the "Woodward Report" include minutes of the Committee on Freedom of Expression, some correspondence, and a copy of the report itself. The files on graduate students of Woodward while he was at Yale are arranged by last name of student. They contain correspondence that should be used with correspondence found under the student's name in Series I. As with that correspondence, there is substantive discussion between Woodward and his students about research undertaken and planned, and professional accomplishments.
  - Aptheker, Herbert, 1944-1979, undated (Box 85, Folder 1 - 4)
  - Committee on Freedom of Expression, 1969-1975 (Box 85, Folder 5)
  - Course notes on the South [includes historiographical notes and writings], 1965, 1976, undated (Box 85, Folder 6 - 8)
  - Dick, Wayne [freedom of speech case], 1986-1994, undated (Box 86, Folder 9)
  - Financial, 1960-1964 (Box 86, Folder 10)
  - History 180, 1962-1971, undated (Box 86, Folder 11)
  - Job offer and negotiations, 1959-1962, undated (Box 86, Folder 12)
  - Graduate standing committee, undated (Box 86, Folder 13)
  - Graduate students
    - Bode, Frederick, 1965-1969 (Box 86, Folder 14)
    - Carlton, David, 1976-1980 (Box 86, Folder 15)
    - Claus, Ruth, 1971-1982, undated (Box 86, Folder 16)
    - Crofts, Dan, 1968-1972 (Box 86, Folder 17)
    - Engs, Robert, 1968-1972 (Box 86, Folder 18)
    - Fields, Barbara, 1972-1981, undated (Box 86, Folder 19)
    - Flock, Sally, 1977-1978 (Box 86, Folder 20)
    - Green, James, 1968-1978 (Box 86, Folder 21)
    - Hackney, Sheldon, 1963-1967 (Box 87, Folder 22)
    - Hahn, Steven, 1976-1981 (Box 87, Folder 23)
    - Holt, Thomas, 1970-1978 (Box 87, Folder 24)
    - Huffman, Frank, 1969-1975 (Box 87, Folder 25)
    - Kousser, J. Morgan, 1970-1975, undated (Box 87, Folder 26)
    - Kruman, Marc, 1974-1981, undated (Box 87, Folder 27)
    - Leonard, Marilyn, 1971-1976 (Box 87, Folder 28)
    - Levy, Eugene, 1965-1970 (Box 87, Folder 29)
    - Martin, John E., 1966-1971 (Box 87, Folder 30)
    - McCarthy, John, 1965-1970 (Box 87, Folder 31)
    - McCormick, Richard L., 1973-1982 (Box 87, Folder 32)
    - McFeely, William, 1963-1967 (Box 87, Folder 33)
    - McTigue, Geraldine, 1975-1980 (Box 87, Folder 34)
    - Nicklason, Fred, 1964-1969, undated (Box 87, Folder 35)
    - Palmer, Bruce, 1968-1980 (Box 87, Folder 36)
    - Pope, Robert Dean, 1974-1976 (Box 87, Folder 37)
    - Powell, Lawrence, 1970-1980 (Box 87, Folder 38)
    - Redkey, Edwin, 1965-1969, undated (Box 88, Folder 39)
    - Rodgers, Daniel, 1970-1974, undated (Box 88, Folder 40)
    - Satterfield, Richard, 1961, undated (Box 88, Folder 41)
    - Schreiber, Stephen, 1968-1972 (Box 88, Folder 42)
    - Thornton, J. Mills, 1969-1978 (Box 88, Folder 43)
    - Thurber, Bert, 1967-1974 (Box 88, Folder 44)
    - Walker, Helen C. ("Cam"), 1967-1971 (Box 88, Folder 45)
    - Wayne, Michael, 1974-1982, undated (Box 88, Folder 46)
    - Weinstein, Allen, 1963-1967, undated (Box 88, Folder 47)
    - Wilentz, Sean, 1976-1977, undated (Box 88, Folder 48)
    - Williams, John, 1963-1967, undated (Box 88, Folder 49)
    - Woodbury, Robert, 1965-1966 (Box 88, Folder 50)
    - Worthman, Paul, 1966-1974 (Box 88, Folder 51)
    - Lists of graduate student names and publications, 1997 (Box 88, Folder 52)
    - Sabbatical [corresondence with graduate students about], 1971, undated (Box 88, Folder 53)
  - Lynd, Staughton, 1968, undated (Box 88, Folder 54)
  - Yale Historical Publications, 1963-1964 (Box 88, Folder 55)
  - Yale University Library, 1959-1962, undated (Box 88, Folder 56)
- Personal, 1804-2000; Series VI
  The series is arranged alphabetically by topic. The Biographical folder includes a 1931 letter from Arthur Raper recommending that Woodward do research in the South for the Commission on Interracial Cooperation, and several vitae. There are two folders of essays about Woodward, mostly pertaining to his work as a historian of the South, written by both professional historians and undergraduate students. The family materials include a miscellaneous assortment of letters, diaries, and clippings related to Vann family members. Interviews include one done by the Atlanta Journal-Constitution in 1997, and one done by Jim Green for Radical History Review. Both provide revealing information on Woodward's early family life, relations with other professional historians, and the development of his theories regarding the South. There are six folders of clippings about Woodward, broadly organized by range of dates, that primarily relate to his career as a historian.
  Original audio tapes in Boxes 95 and 96 may not be played. Readers may only play use copies. Use copies do not exist, therefore researchers must consult with the reference archivist about policies and procedures regarding the creation of duplicating master and use copies of the original recordings.
  - Awards [includes honorary degrees], 1952-1997 (Box 89, Folder 1 - 2)
  - Biographical, 1931, 1996, undated (Box 90, Folder 3)
  - Claremont College, 1942 (Box 90, Folder 4)
  - Education [term paper], undated (Box 90, Folder 5)
  - Essays about C. Vann Woodward, 1969-1980 (Box 90, Folder 6 - 7)
  - Family
    - General, 1848-1997, undated (Box 90, Folder 8)
    - Diaries [Ida and Bess Vann], 1804, 1884, 18--? (Box 90, Folder 9)
    - Vann, Mrs. J. M. [letters to], 1891-1894 (Box 90, Folder 10)
    - Vann, R. V. [certificate of commission as county supervisor], 1873 (Box 91, Folder 11)
  - Former students [list], undated (Box 92, Folder 12)
  - Government-military service, 1942-1945, undated (Box 92, Folder 13)
  - Home library, 1943 (Box 92, Folder 14)
  - Interviews, 1983, 1997 (Box 92, Folder 15)
  - Johns Hopkins University [committee report, syllabi, lecture notes], 1951-1953, undated (Box 92, Folder 16)
  - Journal [kept while at Queens College, Oxford], 1954-1955 (Box 92, Folder 17)
  - National Institute of Arts and Letters, 1954 (Box 92, Folder 18)
  - Ninetieth birthday [includes photographs], 1987-1988 (Box 92, Folder 19)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 92, Folder 20)
  - Portrait unveiling [includes photograph of portrait], 1996 (Box 92, Folder 21)
  - Princeton University [re: job offer], 1959 (Box 92, Folder 22)
  - Scripps College, 1939-1942, undated (Box 92, Folder 23)
  - University of Pittsburgh [re: job offer], 1956 (Box 92, Folder 24)
  - Volunteers for Stevenson [one piece of correspondence], undated (Box 92, Folder 25)
  - Wedding presents, undated (Box 92, Folder 26)
  - Woodward, Glenn, 1982 (Box 92, Folder 27)
  - Clippings about C. Vann Woodward, 1938-1947 (Box 93, Folder 28 - 29)
  - Clippings about C. Vann Woodward, 1954-1999, undated (Box 94, Folder 30 - 33)
  - Memorial service
    - Program, 2000 (Box 94, Folder 34)
    - Audio tape of service, 2000 (Box 95)
    - Audio tape of service, 2000 (Box 96)
- Additional material, 2004; Accession 2005-M-082
  This addition consists of printed materials relating to the C. Vann Woodward Symposium which honored the Yale historian and marked the opening of the C. Vann Woodward Papers in Manuscripts and Archives. The symposium, co-sponsored by the Department of History, Yale University, and Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, was held on October 1, 2004. Panelists included noted historians and former students of Woodward who focused on Woodward's role as a subject of biography and as mentor for other scholars of history.
  - Invitation, program, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Publicity, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Remarks of John Roper [panelist in absentia], 2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Selections from the C. Vann Woodward Papers" [photocopies of correspondence bound as handout], 2004 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Additional material, 1994; Accession 2011-M-067
  - "South Talk" with Dr. Charles Joyner with Special Guest C. Vann Woodward. Coastal Carolina University., 1994; 7 (Box 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
    - Use Copy, 1 (Box 1U)